Guide to the Roscoe Conkling Simmons Papers, 1919-1950 RL.11016
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Roscoe Conkling Simmons papers
1919-1950 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
Simmons, Roscoe Conkling
RL.11016
2.5 Linear Feet
Roscoe Conkling Simmons was an African American orator, journalist, and community leader who strongly supported the Republican party in the early twentieth century. This collection consists of pamphlets, speeches, newspaper clippings, and other ephemera documenting his public life and service to the Republican party.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Collection Overview
The collection consists largely of printed materials, particularly pamphlets, flyers, and newspapers, documenting Simmons' public life as a Republican party organizer and orator. A small number of printed speeches and a file with portraits of Simmons are also included. Materials are loosely arranged by format. Several newspaper clippings include articles and essays by Simmons.
Provenance
The Roscoe Conking Simmons Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in April 2015.
Historical note
Roscoe Conkling (sometimes spelled Conklin) Simmons was born in Greenview, Mississippi, in 1878, and was a nephew of Booker T. Washington' third wife. Simmons graduated from Tuskegee Institute in 1899. He became a prominant journalist for newspapers like the Chicago Defender, the Washington Times-Herald, and the Chicago Tribune. He was also a lifelong Republican. He was a popular orator in the African American community and served as a director of the Republican National Committee's Colored Speakers Bureau for presidential campaigns between 1924 and 1936. Simmons died in April 1951.
African American orators; African Americans -- History; African Americans -- Politics and government; African Americans -- Portraits; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Simmons, Roscoe Conkling; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ) -- History -- 20th century
- Event programs, 1924-1950 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Programs, pamphlets, and other collected materials documenting Simmons' public life, largely featuring him as a lecturer or guest speaker. Other programs appear to be from events he attended.
- Event flyers and advertisements, 1929-1949 (Box 1)
  Flyers and advertisements, largely ephemeral and broadsides, promoting events and other occasions featuring Simmons and other Republican-minded speakers.
- Portraits and pictures, undated (Box 1)
  Formal portraits of Simmons from throughout his life, undated.
- Speeches, 1919-1950 (Box 1)
  Reprints of speeches by Simmons, as well as a typescript of "Address to the Country," and an accompanying attendance list, from a Republican conference in 1950 held in Washington, D.C.
- Pamphlets, 1930s-1940s (Box 1)
  Includes assorted political pamphlets, one authored by Simmons. Titles include: The Republican Party and American Colored People, 1856-1936, by R.C. Simmons; Our Motto: Co-operation, by the Second Ward Republicatn Organization of Chicago; The Story of Roosevelt and Garner as it Affects the Negro, by the Repulican National Committee; and The Negro and the Republican Party, by the Republican National Committee.
- Campaign clippings, 1943 and undated (Box 1)
  Excerpts from The Union newspaper promoting Simmons as a delegate candidate for the Republican National Convention.
- Songsheets and music, 1940s (Box 1)
  Sheet music and lyrics from political events, including a song about Calvin Coolidge.
- The Union (Chicago) newspaper issues, 1928-1948; 3 folders (Box 2)
  Includes assorted issues of The Union, usually with columns by Simmons or advertisements promoting an upcoming speech. The latest issue is dated 1978, but this appears to be a typesetting error. Its estimated date is 1948.
  Access Restrictions
  Newspapers are folded, brittle, and in fragile condition. Digital reproductions may need to be produced to allow access to the materials.
- Second Ward Times (Chicago) newspaper issues, 1938 (Box 3)
  Includes issues with coverage of Simmons' speeches and appearances.
- The Spokesman (Chicago) newspaper issues, 1933 (Box 3)
  Includes issues with Simmons' column "The Week."
- The St. Louis American newspaper issues (Box 3)
  African Americans -- Politics and government; African American orators; African Americans -- History
- Miscellaneous newspaper issues, 1922-1941 (Box 3)
  Includes press coverage of Simmons' lectures as well as published copies of his column "The Week."